[Music]
a
hello good evening good day everybody
and welcome to the latest episode of
asab today we talk about science
astrophysics cosmology technology AI all
that good stuff I hope you're all doing
very well let us see as usual first of
all who else who all is there on the
live chat I can see om beera Prav Vishal
Kumar Verma Sal salong simong sangam
from nagaland Hello tanjiro liberal
mongel by Abhijit chav Vladimir Abhijit
Chava pamel nandi Shri Watson Muhammad
ismile Namaste space KGB agent my nephew
or niece is
it uh DJ Singh sidhar sarar kti K sha K
Joi Shri ramachandra namah Tas swapnil
Mishra hello Tas hello chinki gorov
Sharma Akash Anonymous gorov niket D
Singh
Priyanka pral tier games chandrakar tii
gaku g shat rudan rudra Cole rala ainash
Captain America anul sinari
chasti bhat Satya 20 Sam achara maana
Hain
Al geopolitical duat Pand Gan VI Sagar
dond
tanjiro Ajit Singh Vin Kumar HS my
vision Atif raan Rahul Sharma DHA
strangely proton mavin kumal niharika V
insan King jatin and everybody else I'm
going to stop here otherwise I'm going
to do do this forever so as you I hope
know I'm going to take questions from
the comments that you have uh the
questions that you have put in the
comments over the past week or so so uh
let us get going with that and let's
find what's where's the first question
do we have question number
one okay this is by Amit Singh Amit
Singh is a high school student recently
I was studying Heisenberg's certainty
principle and I found that in Resnik and
holiday book it was given as Delta x *
Delta p is greater than equal to hross
and the same is given in iov's book but
also in some books it was given as Delta
X time Delta p is greater than equal to
H Cross by
2 uh yes so it would be nice if you
could clarify this right so rnck and
holiday is a wonderful book I have it
somewhere over here I think it's this
one here this one this is I think it's
uh I think it's the sixth edition I
don't know which Edition is out right
now must be the 28th Edition or the 73rd
Edition it just goes on every year this
one here is the sixth edition if I'm not
mistaken and it's a great book it's a
great book if you are a high school
student or a college student okay but
it's not the most rigorous book that you
will
find so it want tell you how to derive
the the Heisenberg's uncertainty
principle and it it's it's going to give
you a
heuristic uh view of the Heisenberg
uncertainty principle but not the exact
uh accurate thing so uh let's let's uh
search on Google for the correct
formula I one second let me put that on
the screen so that you can also take a
look at what I'm doing okay let's go to
Google I'm going to search for the
uncertainty principle
Heisenberg uncertainty principle all
right let's go to images and let me show
you that this is the correct thing this
is how it is supposed to be so
uncertainty in position times
uncertainty in in momentum is greater
than or equal to H upon 4 Pi which is H
cross upon two where H cross is the
reduced plank constant okay so that is
the correct uh equation or formula for
the Heisenberg uncertainty principle now
what you find is uh
so uh that's that's the deal that's the
fundamental thing now Heisenberg's
uncertainty principle is a fundamental
Concept in quantum mechanics it's it
asserts that there's a fundamental limit
to the Precision with which certain
pairs of physical properties such as uh
known as complement variables such as
position and momentum or energy and time
these can be simultaneously known so the
hburg UNC uncertainty principle sets
fundamental limits on the Precision by
by at which we can measure various
phenomena so this principle highlights
the intrinsic probabilistic nature of
quantum mechanics of quantum systems and
uh you know there's a breakdown of
causality sometimes over there because
it's a very prob probabilistic there are
random numbers Etc involved in this and
this principle arises from the
non-commuting nature of quantum
operators okay so addition subtraction
Etc it doesn't entirely work uh so to
really understand how the principle is
derived you have to understand various
Concepts like complex numbers you have
to understand expectation values quantum
mechanical expectation values you do
understand statistical Concepts like
variance and standard deviation you do
understand what hermion operators are
you have to know the Koshi Schwartz
inequality you to understand the
position momentum commutation relation
and so on and so forth okay so if you
understand all this then you can
actually see how the principle was
derived and then you will see that uh
the one that's given in Resnik and
holiday is not entirely correct but the
one that I just put on the screen just a
while ago this where is it this one here
this one this is correct okay and hross
is the reduced plank constant the
reduced part so H is the plank constant
and its value is
6.62 * 10us 34 JW seconds and the
reduced plank constant is about 1 * 10-
34 Jewel seconds so there's not much of
a difference there so you can see that
it's approximately correct so that's why
certain books give it this way and
certain books give it that way but like
I showed the one that I put on the
screen just now that is the correct uh
equation for the Heisenberg uncertainty
principle all right uh let's take uh the
next
question the next question is by pratus
R and the question is uh can you shed
some light on the first fmy Paradox and
what does it really talk about okay the
fmy Paradox the fery Paradox is where's
everybody that's the firming Paradox so
we have gazillions of galaxies and
bazillions of stars in the observable
universe okay and assuming each star has
one one planet you have more than 10
rais to 20 one more than 10 ra to 20 two
planets that should exist in the
observable universe and even if life
exists on one out of a billion of these
planets or one of out of a trillion of
these planets that's still 10 raised to
what eight or nine planets that's one
with eight or nine zeros after it those
many planets where life should exist and
if intelligent life is one in a million
then there should still be a thousand or
10,000 or so or maybe 100,000 planets
where you have intelligent life that
exists so if life is so abundant Etc so
on so on so so so on so forth then where
is life where is the intelligent life
out there in the universe we have been
looking at the night sky and staring at
the night sky for centuries and we have
very powerful instruments today
telescopes and detectors and whatnot
which look at the universe in a variety
of different wavelengths and frequencies
we look at the the James web Space
Telescope looks at the universe through
the in the infrared SP you know U part
of the spectrum we have the the the
Chandra x-ray telescope which looks at
the world the universe through x-rays
through x-ray eyes you have Hubble that
looks at the universe through mostly
visible wavelengths and so on so forth
so we have been looking for so long we
have radio telescopes we have everything
and we have not yet detected a single
sign of Life anywhere of intelligent
life of Intelligent Communication of
some kind of message or signal that uh
indicates that it was sent by an
intelligent you know intelligent but
from an intelligence technologically
advanced intelligence
so that's the question and that's the
fir me Paradox if the world if the
universe should be crawling with aliens
all over the place then where is
everybody where are they why have we
detected nothing that's the for me
Paradox and there's something called the
Drake equation the Drake equation let's
put that on the screen right one second
let me
uh okay let's go and try and search for
the Drake
equation okay where's the Drake equation
I'll put that on the screen so
Drake
equation and let's put that on the
screen so I'll not go into the the
details of what this all means but this
tells you uh how
many it essentially tells you how many
intelligent civilizations should exist
in the Galaxy right now in our galaxy
The Milky Way
galaxy uh and yeah so depending on what
parameters you fit in there you will get
get various numbers and the question is
if if if this is there and if if there
should be the so and so number of
intelligent civilizations out there in
the Milky Way then why has nobody
contacted us why is there no signal no
sign of them out there that is the
Paradox so that is the fir me Paradox it
was first I believe proposed I mean the
the question was first raised by wolf
Kang POI one of the great Geniuses one
of the Giants who who on who is
responsible for the for our
understanding of the Quantum world and
much more and yeah so that's a for me
Paradox and there are various Pro
solutions that have been proposed that
for maybe intelligent life is way too
intelligent for us to understand it so
imagine that you are a science student
in a high school or college College
laboratory laboratory you have a
microscope and you're observing a petri
dish or a or a slide full of in which
you have bacteria so you are looking
looking in there and you can observe
those bacteria going about their lives
on that slide under the microscope and
those bacteria are completely unaware of
the fact that they are being observed
they have no idea whatsoever that that
there is something called vision and
that there are there are beings with
with eyes who can visualize things in in
various wavelengths who are observing us
they have no idea whatsoever so maybe we
are like those bacteria and there are
super intelligences out there that are
currently observing us and we have no
idea at all all because 96% of the
universe is the Dark Sector dark energy
plus dark matter and maybe there are
dark dark scientists and dark
civilizations out there completely made
up of dark matter or maybe dark energy
as well and they are undetectable to us
but they can detect us somehow because
they're so Advanced and they are
observing us maybe and we not aware
that's one
possibility that we are being observed
when we are not aware of it secondly
another possibility is that maybe these
aliens uh for them we like bacteria so
they may they may be aware of our of our
existence but they may not be interested
in communicating with us because I mean
do we try to communicate with bacteria
do we try to communicate with
caterpillars we don't right do we try to
communicate with ants we don't doesn't
doesn't uh you know it doesn't interest
us similarly for them maybe we are not
interesting we are we are like bugs in
in a zoo or something like that so maybe
that's another possibility another
possibility is that maybe uh there are
certain filters that civilizations have
to go through fil so for us to reach
where we have
reached you know life had to emerge on
the planet we don't know how life
emerged then from unicellular organisms
we had to evolve into multicellular
organisms our ancestors far away
ancestors deep an deep ancestry and they
to survive various cataclysms and and U
Extinction events on the planet the
great oxygen oxygenation catastrophe and
various uh various uh Extinction events
then the multicellular organisms had to
emerge out of the ocean onto onto land
and they had to ward off various
Predators blah blah blah all that stuff
and then they had to then our ancestors
you know after they had to survive the
chick shulu impact event 66 million
years ago and then they had to become
bipedal walking on two legs and develop
big brains and then we had to develop
various Technologies as human
beings a variety of our close relatives
like the Neanderthals and Homo habilis
Homo erectus hom whatever else they all
passed out they all died out but we
survived Homo sapiens and then we have
been able to develop various
Technologies it's essentially in the
last 120 years since 1900 we suddenly
discovered something called the quantum
world and that's where that's why we
have all this technology today we had to
pass through all these stages and today
we are at the brink of you know we have
certain certain very dangerous weapons
we have nuclear weapons
gazillion truckload of nule nuclear
weapons we have have that more than
10,000 nuclear warheads exist on the
planet then we have human mediated
climate change which could significantly
alter our climate and cause all kinds of
problems for our future generations and
that could conceivably lead to the
extinction of humanity even nuclear war
could lead to the extinction of humanity
so there are all these filters great
filters they are called and it it it's
possible that every civilization has to
go through these great filters and
eventually they all die out because of
this that's another possibility and one
more possibility is that we are the only
intelligent civilization out there in
the entire universe which is a
frightening possibility but who knows we
don't know right so it's all speculation
right now so that essentially all of
that what I just described is the Furby
Paradox and that's what it is talking
about where is everybody where is
everybody why why don't we see anyone
that's a that's a question all
right okay Tas says when will we
actually start mining resources from
other planets or asteroids effectively
okay where are we right now what is the
current situation when it comes to space
exploration so we have the International
Space Station in orbit around the Earth
yes and it's a it's it's a collaboration
of a number of countries uh that has
given rise to the International Space
Station so we generally have what three
two or three human beings in orbit
around the Earth at any given point in
time whether it's two or three or four I
don't remember let's say it's three
three we have three people in orbit
around the Earth and we have a handful
of countries that have human space
flight capabilities the US is one Russia
is one Russia uses that for commercial
purposes it feres American and other
astronauts to space typically through
its so launch Vehicles so the Russians
have that uh ability the Americans have
the ability you have SpaceX which is a
private thing player as well the Chinese
have the ability the Europeans also have
the ability to launch human humans into
space and that's about it the European
space agency India in a year or two will
will start its own human space flight
program so we have one space station one
single two space stations the Chinese
have a smaller one but they it's also a
space station so kudos to China to have
developed that so you have the European
you have the International Space Station
and the Chinese space station in orbit
around the Earth right now the Russians
don't have one right now they they can
build one if they want to but right now
that's not on high on their list of
priorities India will have one in one in
a decade or so by 2030 2035 India may
have a space station of some kind so we
currently are in a position to send
humans to low earth orbit okay uh 200
kilometers above the surface 300 km
about the surface roughly roughly give
or take um the US is planning to send
human human beings back to the Moon in a
couple of years maybe next year maybe
2026 something like that the Artimus
missions and all that uh
so by within this decade we will have
the return most likely of human beings
on the moon so humans will once again
set foot on the moon and eventually by
the 2030s you will have a spa some kind
of a space Colony or some kind of
outpost on the moon that seems to be the
plan by the 2030s uh Russia and China
will also most likely want to be on the
moon have a presence on the moon human
presence on the Moon by 2040 India wants
to have a human presence on the moon at
least have one landing on the moon so
that's where we are right now we are at
a very early initial rudimentary
Elementary phase of space exploration
right now we don't even have a presence
on our nearest uh you know neighbor
which is our own Moon our own satellite
we don't even have a presence there and
the next step is obviously either Venus
or Mars and Mars is much more enticing
because it makes more sense because it
is more earthlike and uh it doesn't have
a horrifyingly hot atmosphere and so on
so that's where we are so first step is
Moon then by the 2030s 2040s we start
hopefully having a presence on Mars now
the asteroid belt exists between the
orbits of Mars and Jupiter and that's
way out there and the asteroid belt is
extremely empty essentially it's
essentially empty space there are
millions of these fragments of rocks
rocks in various sizes some are large
some are tiny and so on but that's
spread out over a gigantic piece of you
know uh real estate in the solar system
and it's mostly empty you know asteroids
are millions of kilometers apart from
each other that's the average distance
uh separation between any two randomly T
randomly taken asteroids that are
neighbors of each other
so it is right now very difficult for us
to even reach the moon then we will to
reach Mars which is even more difficult
and then to reach an asteroid will take
I don't know at least a couple of
decades to just reach one asteroid and
then to deploy the of mining equipment
and all that stuff out there and and
extract that and bring it back to Earth
will I don't know the technology will
take at least 50 years 100 years so the
way things are asteroid mining is
extremely far away in the future it's
not going to happen anytime soon uh I'm
not saying it won't happen maybe in the
2100s you will have large scale asteroid
mining uh if we develop the Technologies
reasonably well and we don't uh we we
still survive we don't come across one
of the great filters of the Paradox so
it's possible but it's going to be a
long time before this happens before
this becomes viable and feasible and
before it becomes commercially viable so
I would say 100 years perhaps I hope I'm
wrong but I would say 100 years at
least okay vant Kulkarni has a number of
questions firstly if the universe is
infinite and uniformly filled with stars
why is the night sky dark and this is
the oldur par Paradox okay so this
question I don't know who oldur was or
whatever I don't remember the history I
mean I don't know but the question is so
a 100 years ago 200 years ago 500 years
ago it was believed that the universe is
infinite okay at least in the West in in
Europe I don't get go get into the
cultural thing part of this thing but it
was believed that the Universe was
infinite and if the universe is
infinite it's a steady state universe
it's not evolving it's just the way it
is sitting around it's in in itely large
then then then it would mean that there
are infinitely many stars out there so
if there's an infinite number of stars
out there in the universe and there are
different distances from here and
eventually all of that light will reach
the planet Earth okay and there won't be
any red shift because there's no
movement of the Stars away from us or
any blue shift because they're coming
towards us they're just stuck wherever
they are you know in the firmament
so to say so if there's an infinite
number of stars in an infinite Universe
then should not should this night sky
not be completely bright why is it dark
that's the Paradox okay logically if
there's infinite number of stars then we
should be Blinded By the Light because
all that light should eventually reach
us but it doesn't the night sky is dark
there just pin Pricks pin Points of
Light so that is the Paradox and the
resolution is very clear that the very
simple that the Universe isn't infinite
we have a we we have an observable
Horizon the observable universe which is
about 90 light years in diameter 45 90
million billion light years in diameter
45 billion light years in radius that's
how that's how far we can see in the
universe and then then also there also
the fact that the universe is expanding
in the acceler the expansion is
accelerating which causes a red shift
and that ensures that even that that
much of the light of the far away stars
is red shifted is stretched out which
makes much of it invisible unless unless
we have something like the James web
Space Telescope that looks at the
universe in the infrared wavelength and
so on so that is the resolution to the
oldur Paradox first of all the universe
is not infinite there's an finite
observable universe and the universe is
expanding and the ex expansion is
accelerating all of that taken together
ensures that the that the Paradox is
resolved so that's the answer to the
ulur
Paradox okay next question is how does
the black hole information Paradox
challenge our understanding of black
holes and the quantum mechanics so the
black hole information Paradox is about
uh well it's it's when we when we come
at the intersection of quantum mechanics
and uh and general relativity that's
that's where we have the the black hole
information Paradox so what what is it
like so quantum mechanics tells tell us
that Quantum information is conserved
you know Quantum information like means
what is the mass of an elementary
particle what is the charge and spin of
an elementary particle what's the
angular momentum and various Quantum
States and all that if you have an atom
then what Quantum States state is the
atom in if it has just one electron like
the hydrogen atom then
what what state is the electron and is
it in the ground state is it in the
first excited state second third fourth
if it's a multi electron atom what are
the various states of the various
electrons all of this is called Quantum
information Quantum States then you have
something like if if it's just a photon
then what's the polarization of the
photon and in what direction in what
plane are is the electric field and the
magnetic field these two fields in what
plane are they oscillating and so on so
all of this is called Quantum
information and according to Quantum
Mechanics which is a very very very
powerful and very well tested Theory
very accurate Theory theory that really
works from so from the perspective of
quantum mechanics Quantum information
should be conserved
Quantum information cannot be cannot
disappear it has to be
conserved
now now when we talk about general
relativity then we have a
situation black hole okay so from the
perspective of black hole th
thermodynamics a black hole is described
by only three properties Mass charge
angular momentum that's it that's it
nothing else Mass charge angular
momentum if angular momentum is zero
then the black hole is not spinning and
it's SW ch black hole in which it's in
which case uh it's it's uh various
properties are given by
mgc uh and so on uh so a black hole is
defined by only these three properties
Mass charge angular momentum what about
the quantum information let's say you
have electrons falling into a black hole
you have let's say the black hole has an
accretion disc around it and it's
swallowing massive quantities of
hydrogen gas and various other kinds of
gases and dust and whatnot it's
absorbing it's it's swallowing photons
what happens to all this Quantum
information once all this gets inside
the black
hole what happens with the information
because the black hole is is described
only by by the mass Char charge and
angular momentum and then Stephen
Hawking showed that black holes actually
radiate they evaporate black holes over
temperature and they evaporate through a
process called Hawking radiation and
whatever the whatever comes out of the
black hole whatever radiation comes out
of the black hole is black body
radiation which is random
which is probabilistic it's
random okay and it doesn't encode the
information that fell inside the quantum
information that fell inside so here you
have a breakdown apparent breakdown of
quantum mechanics so there is a dis
disconnect and discontinuity between
general relativity and quantum mechanics
and that is the black hole information
Paradox and that tells us that either
there's either a problem with quantum
mechanics or with general relativity so
we either need to improve quantum
mechanics there's a flaw somewhere in
there and we need to fix that or we need
to fix some flaw in general relativity
and it looks like the fla maybe May
perhaps lie in general relativity or
maybe both
places we know there's something called
a singularity in general relativity a
singularity is what lies at the heart of
a black hole okay deep inside we pass
the Event Horizon at the center of the
black hole and that's where uh the
curvature of space time becomes infinite
and matter density or energy density
becomes infinite and when you have an
Infinity in in
mathematics it's a division by zero
which means your equations have broken
down you're dividing something by zero
which means there's a flaw in your
theory so clearly um general relativity
which is a brilliant Theory which which
is very very well tested at the large
scales that theory breaks down at the
ultra microscopic
scale so yeah that theory will need some
amendments some improvements but not the
kind of improvements that break the
overall Theory and maybe quantum
mechanics needs to also be you know
changed in some manner modified amended
in some manner there are problems there
are certain issues that are well known
in quantum mechanics I mean for example
gravity doesn't emerge out of quantum
mechanics there's no you can only use if
you can use gravity in quantum mechanics
you can have gravitational potentials
and all but you have to use them you to
use the neutronian potential or you to
use a classical potential and even when
it comes to time in in general Rel
relativity you have space time the four
dimensions of space time three
dimensions of space one dimension of
time in quantum mechanics time is an
external parameter it's a classical
parameter it doesn't emerge
intrinsically out of the theory and so
on so that tells us that there's a lot
that needs to be done when it comes to
try we ideally want to find a unified
theory that that U that reconciles these
two extremely successful theories
quantum mechanics and general Rel
relativity so we want a theory of
quantum gravity what is a theory nobody
knows right now there's a lot of work
that's been done on string theory which
kind of attempts to to give us a quantum
theory of gravity but yeah string theory
has its own limitations and we can talk
about that later so yeah that's the deal
about with the black hole information
Theory theorem black hole information
Paradox now the third question is if
time slows down near a massive object
due to gravitational time dilation how
do we reconcile this with the idea of a
singularity at the center of a black
hole where time is said to
stop okay
so the time dilation is is it's
something that you will find in the
special theory of relativity you don't
even have to go to uh general relativity
to see time dilation time dilation
effects are visible you can see in
special relativity itself and it has
nothing to do with the singularity which
maybe the the which may exist at the
center of a black hole uh time dation
effects uh and of course time dilation
also exists in general relativity which
is the actual proper Theory so time
dilation happens when you are going at
extremely higher velocities or when you
are in the presence of a very large mass
or any Mass so Mass see in general
relativity the entire universe exists on
a stage or in a stage which is spacetime
four dimensions and SpaceTime gets
curved when there is a presence of
matter in it so so so matter curves
SpaceTime and the curvature of SpaceTime
tells matter how to move and this
curvature of space time is what we feel
as the force of gravity Newtonian
gravity we feel it like that but it's
actually the curvature of space time in
four dimensions not three dimensions or
two Dimensions okay so uh time dilation
happens because of the curvature of
space time and you can look at the
equations if you're really interested
it's not because of a singularity you
can have a mass that has that doesn't
have any Singularity okay if you have a
mass m and the let's say it's a
spherical object but the spherical
object its radius is greater than its
Schwartz chill radius then it's not a
black hole and there's no Singularity
there and you will still have time
dilation so you don't need you don't
need to reconcile time dilation with
singularities okay a singularity is a
whole different thing it's it's an
artifact that emerges out of the
Einstein field equations and clearly
there is some something that needs to be
improved in these equations and what it
is we still don't know so there you have
it okay it's it's uh the the two things
aren't correlated time dation if if you
do away with Singularity it doesn't mean
that time dilation will go away time
dilation exists because of mass or
because of well
inertial frames of reference if you have
non-inertial or even inertial frames of
reference well to go into this in detail
you'll have to at least study special
relativity because time dilation emerges
very nicely out of that
okay swapnil says how did the alignment
between Saturn and Jupiter impact
Neptune's orbit causing the late heavy
bombardment event okay what is this late
heavy bombardment good question so uh
when the Apollo missions happened when
the Americans sent uh astronauts to the
moon in the 60s and 70s I think when was
the last mission I think early 80s or
late '70s don't remember you can look it
up so let's say the decade of the 70s
late 60s and '70s that's when the Apollo
missions happened you had human beings
going to the moon landing on the moon
and bringing back space Rock moon rocks
Moon soil samples and stuff and these
samples when were then U examined and
tested and
analyzed and what they discovered the
scientists the geologists uh is that
these many of the samples were samples
of molten rock rock that had melted and
then
reformed so
uh and it became clear that there were
gigantic impacts of of asteroids or
meteorites or whatever you want to call
them space rocks on the moon about let's
say about 4 billion years before
today so the Earth Moon system is about
4.5 I think billion years old roughly
roughly okay I may be slightly wrong
here and there you can look it up so
this these phenomena these gigantic
events impact impact events happened
about roughly four billion years before
today and the evidence is found on the
moon but the Moon is right next to the
Earth it's it's it's a satellite of the
earth which means that this bombardment
would have happened on the earth as well
but the Earth's crust in the entire
system is very Dynamic we have water we
have a rich and thick atmosphere and we
have a plate tectonics and lot of
movement and all so all any impact event
will after a few million years maybe
after 100 200 million years disappear
mostly we have some uh some uh impact
creators that are more than a billion
years old which are still which still
exist like the free the fourth crater in
South Africa for example more than a
billion years old but most craters
disappear very rapidly because the uh
because the earth's surface is very
Dynamic so we don't have evidence of
this this bombardment which we call the
late heavy bombardment on Earth but we
can see we have found evidence of that
on the moon now the question is how did
this happen so there's been lots of
simulation of the early solar system and
there's something called the N model
it's named after out of the city of n in
in France and that's where this model
was developed so according to this model
which is a very plausible model you know
uh initially the four gas giant planets
which are the four gas giants can you
can you name the four gas giants well
let me tell you it's Jupiter Saturn
Uranus and Neptune these are the four
gas giant planets in our solar system so
according to the nce model these four
gas giants initially had formed much
closer to the Sun than they are right
now it was a reasonably compact Stellar
system or solar system and obviously the
rocky planets uh Mercury Venus Earth and
Mars were on the inside but those are
actually insignificant when we comp
compare them to the masses of the four
gas giants so the four gas giants had
formed much closer to the Sun than they
are right now and then Jupiter and
Saturn these two planets they uh came
into the what they they came into a
state of resonance so a resonance is
when the orbit of one planet becomes an
integer multiple of the orbit orbital
time period of another planet so let's
say Jupiter its orbital Time Around The
Sun becomes exactly twice the orbital
period of Saturn around the Sun so for
each orbit Saturn takes around makes
around the Sun Jupiter makes two orbits
that sort of thing that's called an
orbital resonance so so Jupiter and
Saturn entered into into this state of
or orbital resonance or orbital
resonance Crossing which means that
there was a crossing of the reson and
this caused an instability in the orbits
of the other two gas giants which were
flung further away and outside on the on
the outside part of the or of the of the
St of the Proto protostellar disc of the
early solar system you had these bodies
called Planet dismals which are like
small dwarf planet like or or
protoplanet like small bodies which
existed in in a large cluster beyond the
orbits of the larger planets and as
Neptune went outside and further away
from the Sun it came into contact with
this planet planet decimals and
disrupted their orbits and this
disruption of their orbits caused the
orbits to get to get elongated develop
High eccentricities to be thrown out of
of the of the plane of the solar system
and also it caused a lot of disruption
and churn in the solar system and it
caused what is believed to be the late
heavy bombardment which is all these
bodies which were outside they were
flung inwards toward the Sun and they
ended up impacting not just Earth and
the moon but maybe also the
other rocky planets within the inner
solar system so that essentially is the
late he heavy bombardment event this is
how this is one model of how it could
have have happened okay uh it still
needs to be seen whether it is correct
but it is the I believe the most popular
and most mainstream Theory the N model
of how how this happened so that's how
the entire thing uh took place according
to this model there was an orbital
resonance Crossing between Jupiter and
Saturn which impacted the orbit of
Neptune which which was flung further
away from the sun and it it ended up
disrupting the orbits of all these
protoplanetary IES and planet dismals
and Rocky objects in the outer solar
system which somehow got flung many of
which got somehow flung towards the
inner solar system and ended up causing
the late heavy bombardment roughly four
billion years before today on the earth
and the moon and probably the other
inner planets as
well okay Rohan BD says when we see
Jupiter through a regular telescope
using the visible spectrum of radiation
what we can see with our eyes that's a
visible spectrum it appears in a certain
way yes when we look at Jupiter through
visible wavelengths what we can perceive
with our eyes it looks in a it looks
like a certain thing right the bands and
the Great Red Spot and all that when we
see when we look at Jupiter through the
James web Space Telescope using infrared
radiation it appears different it
appears yeah the image looks different
and when we use the Chandra Space
Telescope with x-ray radiation it still
looks different it's it's a whole
different image that we see of Jupiter
when what then is the true look of
Jupiter the true appearance the true
shape and form of Jupiter are all or are
all these just Illusions we can never
know what the true picture is and that's
why our scriptures say the world is M
Maya is good question yes all of these
pictures that we see are the correct
picture and the true picture is the
completely composite picture the
superposition of all these pictures so
our eyes they can perceive only a
certain range of frequencies or
wavelengths okay of of infrared of
infrared radiation infrared radiation is
photons photons come in a number of
frequencies or wavelengths frequences
and wavelengths are two sides of the
same
coin uh so photons come in various
frequencies or various wavelengths and
we can perceive through our eyes a
certain range of frequencies which is
visible light you know VI IB g y r that
the rainbow and we also have infrared
radiation which is infrared photons we
have ultraviolet photons which are more
energetic infrared photons are have
longer
wavelengths um and uh smaller
frequencies long yeah no sorry infrared
radiation has longer wavelengths
ultraviolet radiation has shorter
wavelengths and higher frequencies which
are more energetic photons and then you
have x-rays and you have gamma rays and
ultra high energy gamma ray and whatnot
okay that's all the various frequencies
of photons and then we have long wave
radio waves and it it goes in the
opposite end of the spectrum as well but
we can only perceive a certain
range of the entire spectrum of of
electromagnetic radiation which is
photons so what we see is one part of
the True Image and what Hubble and all
these visible light telescopes see is
one small portion of the True Image then
you can use Chandra x-ray wavelengths
and you see a whole different image
that's also the True Image the true
picture but it's a small part of the
true picture so what we see through
visible wavelengths is a small part of
the true picture what you see through
x-ray wavelengths is a different small
part of the true picture when you use uh
when we use infrared radiation like the
James web Space Telescope does we see a
whole different picture which also is
the correct picture so all of these
pictures taken together form the true
picture and we see only through through
our eyes we only see a small part of it
so the world is much more than what we
can perceive and then we have not even
spoken about the gravitational
wavelengths I mean gravitational waves
also exist and we are just beginning to
take baby steps in detecting
gravitational waves and right now we are
in a position to only detect
gravitational tsunamis not waves
tsunamis waves with gigantic amplitudes
so such gravitational waves are only
those that are created by the mergers
and collisions of black holes two black
holes or a black hole in a neutron star
or two neutron stars that sort of
cataclysmic gravitational event throws
up a gigantic gravitational wave tsunami
and that's what we can detect right now
but what I would like to have happen is
we you know to develop the technology
that would allow us to to detect
gravitational ripples in space time
that's when the real Universe emerges so
we have all these wavelengths of visible
light and we have not even spoken about
gravitational waves so all of that taken
together and maybe some other things
also that we may not be aware of all of
that taken together is the true picture
we only see a small tiny fraction of the
true picture so yes from that
perspective the world is entirely M
Maya so good question very good
question okay uh regit banery
says what is quantum Computing and can
it be used to encode the genes of an
unborn baby Quantum Computing so Quantum
Computing does a whole lot of stuff see
Quantum Computing a classical computer
uses I'll just make it as as brief as
possible a classical computer like your
cell phone your uh laptop or whatever
these computers classical computers uh
they use something called bits for for
storing information a bit is either a
one or a zero okay that's what what it
is it's a binary thing binary digit a
bit uh classical computers and these
bits on classical computers they are
stored either in Ram or in some part of
the memory okay and they're manipulated
using Quant using using Gates okay Gates
superc conducting
Gates that's the architecture I mean
that's a very very rudimentary way of
putting forth what the architecture is
in quantum computers we have Quantum
bits so let's say in a classical
computer we have a bit which is either a
one or a zero and if you have two bits
then you get the these possibilities 0 0
0 1 1 0 and 1 one okay that's the
classical computers possibilities with
two bits these are the four possible uh
com four possible combinations of of uh
data information that you will have in
these two bits in a quantum computer a
cubit can be either one it can be either
zero or it can be a superposition of one
and zero at the same time okay and if
you have two cubits when you have all
those position all those all those
possibilities 0 0 0 1 1 0 1 one all
those possibilities exist
simultaneously okay that's one way of
looking at it and so that's that's the
power so you can exponentially increase
the scale of your computations in a
quantum computer and then you take you
use you take advantage of quantum
properties such as superposition and and
uh
entanglement and so on
one uh superposition is there
entanglement wave function collapse and
much more and you have one you have
Quantum gates in quantum computers as
opposed to classical superconducting
Gates you have Quantum Gates uh and you
have Quantum Al algorithms like Shores
algorithm and and Growers algorithm etc
etc etc so that's essentially is how
quantum computers operate you need to
keep the Computing environment
shockingly cold as close to 0 Kelvin as
POS possible otherwise the superp
positions will break down if if any heat
gets in and you could have the
introduction of noise and what not which
will destroy the superp positions and
whatever entanglements you've created
and so on and then you have Quantum
measurements through through Quantum
traps and all that I'll not get get into
all that technical stuff but that's how
a quantum computer works and that's how
it's different from a a classical
computer and quantum computers have
certain advantages that they can perform
certain computations in a finite am
amount of time that classical computer
simply cannot do
so that's what a quantum computer is now
what are the applications of quantum
Computing and where is a quantum
computer Superior to a classical
computer so there's a lot of
applications but you you spoke about
you're speaking about genetics over here
right Quantum Computing and genetics of
babies so genomic data analysis is one
is one application of quantum Computing
Computing now genomic uh sequencing data
when you do genomic sequencing that
generates massive amounts of data okay
all those all those four codes and
whatnot Okay so quantum computers can
process and analyze its data way faster
than classical computers which gives you
much quicker much more rapid insights
into the genetic information that you're
analyzing and there's something called
gene expression new Gene I mean genes
are expressed in under different
conditions okay and how specific genes
are expressed once again you to analyze
massive amounts of data to sift through
all the data and to express how the
genetic expression happens so once again
these complex patterns and correlations
among all this massive amount of data
can can be uh can be unraveled can be
understood can be recognized through
quantum computers and uh Quantum
algorithms it's very difficult to detect
using classical methods because it'll
take way too long then you have
something called Gene networks genes
don't operate in isolation Okay I mean
you you have all this genetic
information in your DNA and genes don't
operate in isolation they operate in
correlation with each other they operate
in complex networks so Quantum Computing
can hopefully help us
unravel uh these Gene networks these
interactions are extremely complex and
classical computers probably just can't
uh you know unravel and and analyze
these so quantum computers can probably
do that which will provide insights into
how various genes influence each other
and contribute to various traits and
various uh immunities and various
genetically inherited diseases and
conditions and whatnot and then there is
evolution so genetics and evolution go
hand in hand so quantum computers can
help uh simulate various complex
evolutionary Pro processes which help us
understand how genetic traits evolve
over multiple Generations let's say
2,000 generations and how does genetic
diversity arise within po over let's say
2,000 or 10,000 Generations you can
simulate all that in a quantum computer
so that's what it is so that's what
quantum computers eventually will be
able to do right now we in the infancy
of this we are right now in the very
beginning the very infancy of quantum
Computing so when when it comes to
encoding the genes of an unborn baby I
don't think that is ethical or even
possible right now because we have to
first understand what I just all all
that stuff that I just outlined Gene
networks and correlations and Cession
and and so much more only then we will
be in a position to safely even think of
safely encoding or or or editing genes
obviously today we have Technologies
like crisper Etc which kind of help
people to edit their own genes which is
very very dangerous and we already have
GMOs genetically modified organisms
typically crops and all that but who
knows what else is is out there so it's
dangerous because we don't it's
dangerous because we don't understand
how changing one specific Gene can
affect everything else because it's a
gene Network it's not a gene in
isolation and it's evolved over millions
of years you just just can't start
playing God and tampering with things so
I would not want Quantum Computing to be
used to to create designer babies or any
such thing we have to well but my saying
or not saying or my you know my
cautioning over here will really not
make much of a difference
unfortunately but that's just how it is
So eventually I'm sure Quantum Computing
will be able to crack all of this
and possibly in the future maybe 20
years 30 years maybe 5 years maybe now
maybe uh capable of of uh telling you
what to do what modifications you may
want to do additions deletions
modifications to the DNA and genes of
organisms to bring about specific
changes it's possible for sure
Rik Paar says what is the technological
singularity how long will it take for us
to reach the singularity after we reach
egi I think AGI is the technological
singularity no technological singularity
means an artificial intelligence
becoming
self-aware self-aware see we are
self-aware aren't we I know that I exist
I know that I am separate from my
environment and I know that I'm a I'm
I'm a I'm a player I'm a participant in
the grand scheme of things I can
actually like Steve Jobs would say make
a dent in the universe through my
actions through Cession and correlation
so I am aware of the fact that I exist
separate and individually from the rest
of the universe and every human being as
far as I as far as we can see uh every
human being is self-aware starting from
infancy I mean I'm when do infants
newborn infants become self-aware I'm
sure pretty soon after they they born we
don't know exactly when but it happens
at a certain given time we know that
dogs and cats and various other animals
are self-aware and that kind of drags us
into the realm of Consciousness which
we'll not go into so self-awareness is
the key so the technological singularity
is when an artificially intelligent
system becomes aware of its own
existence so right now we have these
chat Bots uh whatever the these chat
Bots are chat gbd and whatnot they you
can interact with them through text and
various other means and they talk to you
like a human being which means they have
essentially passed the touring test more
or less and they seem to be self-aware
you ask it philosophical questions about
itself and it's going to respond to you
in some ways like like an reasonably
like like a remarkably intelligent
person actually but doesn't mean that it
is actually self-aware it looks like
it's self-aware that it's a it's
actually just you what these AI systems
are right now it's a whole bunch of
neural networks
essentially equations statistical
equations this matrix multiplication
going on at a massive scale and whatnot
and it's just giving you these are these
are U systems
that give you predictive output
predictive output what is the next best
thing I can I mean the
next the most probable and and the best
possible next character of output what
is it that I can give you and if based
on all this information and data that it
has it has been trained on so it's
essentially just a statistical machine a
statistical machine that seems to be
very intelligent and it's been trained
in that manner but I'm not sure if it's
really self self-aware right right now
you know these AI systems like chat gbt
and Bard and whatever else is out
there but techn the technological
singularity is when an AI system
artificially intelligent machine becomes
genuinely
self-aware okay and that probably is Agi
artificial general intelligence or maybe
at some point after we reach AGI uh I
don't know if that is even possible for
if it is even possible for an artificial
intelligent system to become genuinely
self-aware how would we know it's become
self-aware I mean right now these AI
chat box chat Bots they talk to us like
they're self-aware so how do we know
it's actually self-aware and and what
does it take for an AI system to become
actually self-aware so all that is right
now very much under consideration some
people alleg that some of these AI
systems have already become agis and
self-aware and whatnot but we don't know
right now so once again when we talk
about self- awareness we're talking
about this system becoming conscious of
its own existence Consciousness once
again
and it's possible that machines may
never become conscious the way we are
conscious uh we we have these sense
organs that contribute to our
Consciousness we have memory and we have
an external internal representation of
the outside external world within us and
that is kind of our worldview and that
kind of is our is is the is the
guidelines is it's a map that we use to
chart our way around the world and so on
do AI systems are they capable of having
that or not these are Big questions
exist existential questions
philosophical questions because
Consciousness is philosophy it's not
science yet because we don't have a
definition of Consciousness so these
questions uh we don't have clear answers
to them but we know that AI is very
powerful already and it's going to be
more powerful in the future and we will
have eii systems that are already way
more powerful than we can imagine but
they are secret because uh when a new
technology in emerges it's typically the
governments and the militaries that make
first use of the full potential of the
technology the full capability of the
technology and what's put out there in
the public domain is just a watered down
version so it's possible that AGI may
already have happened but does it mean
that the system is conscious we're not
quite sure of yet so the answer is we
don't know right
now okay next question swapnil says what
is what is chaos theory the butterfly
effect is it mathematically known as it
is mathematically known as sensitive
dependence on initial conditions how
applicable is it scientifically and in
everyday life Chaos Theory chaos theory
is all about
uh so we talk about chaos theory and we
give the metaphor of the butterfly
effect so what is a butterfly effect
let's say I have a butterfly sitting in
a butterfly in a garden in New Delhi and
the Butterfly is fluttering its wings
and this little initial thing that
happens the butterfly is sitting on a
flower and it flutters its wings Rises
up in the air so these are the initial
conditions and eventually it may end up
causing a tornado in
Lahore or in dend or in Beijing let's
say wherever so that's that's the
metaphor that we use to talk about Chaos
Theory the butterfly effect okay so the
sensitivity so these are it's so chaos
theory is essentially a branch of
mathematics okay it deals with systems
that are extremely complex they they
appear to be disordered systems random
systems but they are actually governed
by deterministic
laws okay so that's that's the branch of
mathematics we're talking about chaos
theory and these
systems and let's say we put a timer we
start a clock at time equal to t equal
to Z and then we go forward so the
initial conditions are the conditions
that prevailed in the system at time t
equal to zero and these systems are
extremely sensitive to these initial
conditions extremely large extremely
complex systems appear to be disordered
appear to be random but they are
governed by deterministic laws and
highly sensitive to initial conditions
which means that very small changes that
happen at the start or very small things
that happen at the chart the start at
time t equal to zero can lead to vastly
different outcomes so in in case the
butterfly is flooded the swings like
this or like that that would lead to
vastly different outcomes a tornado in
ra pindy or a tornado in in Shanghai
that sort of thing okay so that is what
it is and we know I mean if you study
the the if you study gases okay the
boltzman
distribution and so on then you will see
that uh these systems are not really
random and unpredictable they are
governed by by by deterministic
uh you know the the these systems are
actually deterministic and you can
statistically analyze them and you can
predict what happens in the future so
that is what a det what this kind of
system is okay and uh even extremely
small infinite deim small differences in
initial conditions can lead to vastly
different outcomes and chaotic systems
there are examples like weather this
climate uh turbulence in in in fluids in
water so all so many of the systems are
governed by what's called nonlinear
equations where the input where the
output is not directly or linearly
proportional to the input and this
nonlinearity of these nonlinear
equations that govern the systems it is
the key factor in the development of
this chaotic Behavior so the study of
weather patterns is one of the most
well-known applications of Chaos Theory
weather systems are chaotic okay and
it's that's why it's so hard to have
accurate weather predictions and such
accurate weather predictions are are
only possible a few days in advance and
a very small change in atmospheric
conditions can drastically alter weather
patterns so you need massive amounts of
computation you need super computers
essentially to model the weather based
on initial conditions uh so so weather
weather prediction is is a big uh it's a
big uh application of Chaos Theory then
there's application of chaos theory in
in biology and ecology population
Dynamics the
fluctuations the fluctuation of species
populations in an ecosystem let's take
the whole of Africa there are so many
different species of animals and birds
and aquatic creatures and insects and
what not out there and all of these are
in a c in a in a state of Quasi
equilibrium but the fluctuations
but these these species their
populations keep fluctuating based on a
lot of different factors so many
different parameters so Chaos Theory can
help us understanding help us in
understand understanding these
population fluctuations once again small
very small tiny changes in various
environment environmental factors like
the amount of precipitation in a certain
region or the temperature of the climate
in a certain region whether it it was
raining or snowing or whether there was
a there was a hail storm whatever that
can lead to massive drastic variations
in the sizes of populations and the and
the fates of various populations of
species so that's another application
then we have fluid dynamics like I said
electrical circuits mechanical systems
all of that can be used um this this
application of chaos the and all that uh
there's economics and finance so
financial markets are chaotic they
exhibit chaotic chaotic behavior and uh
very small changes in investor sentiment
and uh uh external economic factors can
lead to significant fluctuations in
stock prices and market trends so so
many applications of of Chaos Theory
human behavior can be influenced by by
chaotic Dynamics
uh very small changes in environmental
circumstances or individual
circumstances can lead lead to
significant changes in human behavior
and decision making so once again that
is this applications of Chaos Theory
there then uh in in in health in
medicine Chaos Theory can help you
understand the
uh cardiac arithm and epilepsy so
epilepsy is all about brain waves and
chaotic brain waves causes epil
epileptic seizures and when it comes to
cardiac arithm that is deviation from
the steady harmonic pattern of your
heartbeats so when you have
irregularities that is also kind of
chaotic so these are also chaotic
systems the brain waves the the heart uh
lung system and all that so all of this
has Chaos Theory applications so yeah so
that's kind of application of chaos
theory in everyday life stock markets
def definitely everyday life uh weather
patterns definitely everyday life human
behavior very much everyday life right
and uh yeah in certain diseases certain
conditions like epilepsy uh cardiac
arthas and I'm sure there are so many
more applications but I can give you a
few right now there you have it good
question I like it like it yes good
question okay
rajouri says how does a butterfly retain
its memory as a caterpillar even after
getting most of itself digested apart
from a few cells can this be researched
and used to transfer memory in
humans so
butterflies begin as as uh caterpillars
we know that and then they um then they
enter this cocoon phase in which they
they create this silk cocon and and
Encon themselves in these silk cocoons
and then they go through a crysalis
phase and whatnot and then they emerge
as butterflies right so the end product
the butterfly is so visibly different
structurally and architecturally
different from the initial product the
caterpillar right so different but it's
the same organism and the question is
how does a butterfly retain its memory
as a caterpillar after after undergoing
this massive transformation this
metamorphosis and maybe much of it gets
digested apart from a few sales I'm not
sure about that but what happens the
question is the question I want to ask
is how do we know that a butterfly has
any
memory of its past life as a caterpillar
how do we know
that I mean have has any body mapped the
brain of a butterfly and done a one one
to one correspondence with the uh
memories that were there in its brain
when it was a caterpillar and do those
memories persist we don't know that we
don't
know and it's very hard to to understand
how memory Works in
brains if you want to just map a cubic
millimeter of human brain the data
output of the data that comes out of it
is several
terabytes or petabytes I think it's
terabytes like a few hundred terabytes
out of a single cubic millimeter of
human brain and a cubic millimeter of
brain I'm not sure how large a
butterfly's brain is I'm sure it's less
than a cubic millimeter or maybe around
a cubic millimeter I'm not sure but that
too is a tremendous amount of
information how do we map which memory
is where we still aren't there we still
don't have the capability of knowing
which memory is is located in which
specific physical location in a brain
and in what form the memory is stored
it's through neural connections and all
we we still don't have the capability or
the understanding of this so we don't
know if butterflies when they emerge out
of the cocoons have any memory of their
past life as a
caterpillar okay we don't know we have
no knowledge at all as far as I know if
I'm wrong please please let me know in
the comments below and send show me some
references and I'll be happy to educate
myself but as far as I know we we don't
have the understanding of this at
all and yeah there's this philosophical
concept called the ship of thesis right
if you have a ship made of wood and the
ship goes out on voyages and over time
it has wear and tear and you to start
replacing the various components of the
ship of the ship from time to time and
after let's say 50 years or 100 years
the ship still exists but all the
components have been replaced everything
has been replaced so 100 years ago
whatever the ship was made off today
today it's all different materials but
is this is it so the question is is it
the same same shape or is it a different
shape all together now it has a same the
same size the same shape the same
appearance but everything has been
replaced so is it the same ship or is it
a different ship and that applies to us
also because all of our cells keep keep
getting replenished cells die and cells
are reformed and reborn and all that so
so are we the same people am I the same
person I was let's say a decade
ago I I think I am and so on so yeah
these questions they bring in
philosophical musings as well but the
answer is we don't know what Memories a
butterfly has when it emerges as a
butterfly does it have any memories of
its past life of its previous phase of
existence as a caterpillar we don't know
about that we don't
know PR prna says what is string theory
string theory is interesting question
String Theory uh a much maligned uh
branch of physics is is string theory
isn't it uh so String Theory so it's
like
this in in standard physics we talk
about electrons we talk about protons we
talk about neutrons we talk about
electrons and so on this these
fundamental part particles quarks and
all and we represent these
particles as as
points okay Point particles in in
neonian physics in in in the ktic theory
of
gases and even in in particle physics we
we look upon these Elementary particles
and Etc as Point particles okay so that
is
how standard physics or classical and
quantum physics looks at particles as as
Point particles but in string theory we
don't look at particles as Point
particles we we look upon them as uh as
vibrations of
strings
okay
so and and the the vibration of strings
the the different ways in which strings
vibrate one dimensional strings vibrate
these vibrations give rise to different
kinds of
particles so that's the basic basis of
string theory it isn't the fundamental
building block of string theory is not
your point you know Zero Dimensional
Point particles but onedimensional
strings and these strings vibrate
vibrating strings so like a guitar
string if you play a guitar string which
which in there are different ways in
which these strings vibrate and so if
these are your strings of string theory
these vibrations of different modes they
give rise to different kinds of
Elementary
particles now string
theory has space time but very different
space time from what we have in general
relativity in general relativity we have
four dimensional space time three
dimensional of space and one dimension
of time in super String Theory we have
10 dimensional space time so one
dimension of time and nine dimensions of
space the three dimensions that we are
aware of and six more
dimensions of space that
are highly compactified so they are
highly curled up and we we are we are
not able to visualize them we cannot see
them but they exist and they're
extremely compact dimensions that's why
they we are oblivious to their existence
so that's super String Theory 10
dimensional SpaceTime there's something
called M Theory which has 11 dimensional
space time then there's bosonic String
Theory which is 26 dimensional space
time okay and in addition to strings in
string theory we also have higher
dimensional objects called membranes or
brains in short B any brain and these
brains can be of various Dimensions like
a two-dimensional surface or a
three-dimensional volume and strings can
attach to these brains and string theory
also involves a principle called super
Symmetry and according to Super symmetry
every particle every fundamental
elementary particle has a super partner
with a different set of spin properties
with different spin properties and this
helps solve certain theoretical issues
but we have never observed any super
partners or super particles squarks or
or whatever else
photons
electrons we haven't observed any super
Partners ever ever I mean it was the
great hope that the large hydron
collider would give would would bring
forth evidence for super symmetry but
sadly unfortunately that has not
happened okay so that is what string
theory is in a nutshell and there are
big problems with string theory this
theory has been around for for decades
since the 1950s 1960s 60s probably one
of the well the glaring challenge that
string theory faces is the lack of
direct experimental evidence it has
not it has not made any predictions that
have that are
experimentally observe or provable
falsifiable so string theory is not
falsifiable okay so the scales the
physical scales at which the string
theory operates are much smaller than
the scale of an atom
the reach of our experimental
capabilities so even if it makes any
predictions they cannot be
experimentally verified or
falsified so that's one of the major
problems that you face with string
theory and then there's the uh
mathematical complexity extremely the
string theory string theory is highly
mathematical extremely complex lots of
different versions and finding solutions
that describe our universe accurately is
difficult thus far it's proven to be
impossible which brings us to the
landscape problem String Theory land the
string theory landscape the string
theory Multiverse so to say the string
theory allows for a tremendously large
number of possible solutions or
universes okay it it gives a
tremendously large number of possible
solutions this is called the strength
Theory landscape and each of these
Solutions corresponds to us to a
possible possible physical Universe with
different physical laws so each Universe
has
unique set of physical laws and no two
universes are the same and there are 10
raised to I don't know 500 or so such
Universe possible universes that's the
string theory landscape of the string
theory Multiverse which makes it
essentially impossible to determine
which of the solutions describes our
universe and so on so forth so these are
the problems that string theory faces
it's well it's not solved any of our
problems the grand objective of string
theory was to give us a quantum theory
of gravity
and well thus far it's not really I mean
yeah it's wonderful mathematics and all
but it's it's not solved any of our
problems so maybe we need to look Beyond
String Theory all right that's
what okay Rohan VII says to understand
the beginning of the universe we rely on
the radiation reaching us from back then
yes since there was no radiation prior
to the Big Bang or if there was and it
cannot reach us do you think it's
impossible for us to know conclusively
what caused the Big Bang this is a great
question so typically people will ask
what caused the Big Bang right but this
is a better question because this Rohan
over here understands how science works
we need evidence to form
theories so what the standard model of
cosmology the Big Bang model it's all
based on experimental observable
evidence right we have the cosmic
microwave background radiation and so
many other aspects that go into this and
all of that creates the standard model
of the the Lambda CDM model cosmological
model Big Bang Theory model so to
understand the early phases the early
era of our
universe we need data from that time so
we have to rely on the radiation from
that time
period and there was no radiation before
the big Bank
we know that so so there's no data from
that time from before the Big
Bang and even the first few instants
after the big bang before inflation
happened when all four forces were
unified well most likely into a UNIF
unified Grand unified force and then
there was symmetry breaking it is
believed to have happened and then the
forces decoupled one after the other I
mean of that also we we don't really
have uh great amount of evidence for
that uh so yes your question is very
valid and the answer is what you're
suggesting it is it's impossible for us
to know conclusively what caused the Big
Bang as as of today as of today we don't
have any information about that period
of time the very beginning of uh time
itself right obviously there would have
been gravitational waves from that time
SpaceTime existed and SpaceTime was
squeezed into this essentially
almost a
point and uh so SpaceTime existed and
then something caused space time to
expand it was not an explosion it was
expansion and you would have had
gravitational interactions of various
kinds initially it was just pure
energy probably pure Pure Energy what
form would the energy have taken was it
would it be
photons or what not and at some point in
time in the very early Universe
gravitational waves would have uh
emerged and if we can if you can detect
those that Relic gravitational radiation
then that may give us a better Insight
than we currently have about the very
initial conditions of the universe but
uh overall what you're saying is right
we don't have there would be no
radiation of any kind prior to the Big
Bang which essentially means that we
will not be able to know what happened
at the time and what caused the Big Bang
so yeah it's as of today it's impossible
for us as of today to know what cause
the big bang and that is
correct okay Rohan again
says what's the difference between a
super massive black hole at the center
of a galaxy and an active Galactic
nucleus or active Galactic
nuclei so we know that most Galaxies
have a super massive black hole at the
center now super massive black holes are
black holes but they are very massive
like super massive the name itself
suggests how large they are so a super
massive black hole can have a million
solar masses million times the mass of
the Sun or maybe several billions of
solar masses several billion times the
mass of the Sun
um and we know that the Milky Way has
the Sagittarius AAR super massive black
hole which is a few million solar masses
not a very large uh super massive black
hole reasonably small sized super
massive black hole and there are then
there are much bigger ones so that's
your standard super massive black hole
which which is at the at the heart of
most galaxies okay at the center of most
galaxies now there's something called an
active Galactic nucleus AGN so these are
active supermassive black Hol what do I
mean by active so when it comes to
active Galactic nuclei these gal these
these supermassive black holes are
actively
feeding they eating what are they eating
they they're eating material matter
essentially gas and dust gas and dust so
these active Galactic nuclei have
gigantic accretion clouds around them
this
big tornado world poool like
situation all of this gas and dust
Falling Towards the black hole with high
angular momentum extremely high
velocities and relativistic velocities
you know not exactly close to the speed
of light but let's say half the speed of
light or or you know
velocities at which relativistic effects
become visible and apparent so
relativistic velocities extremely high
velocities at which this gas and dust is
is being sucked into the black hole and
very close to the black hole there's
this massive traffic jam of matter which
becomes extremely luminous extremely hot
and much of the the energy of these uh
infalling particles gets converted into
gravit gravitational energy and then
these black holes they are also rotating
and the cloud is also rotating and at
the Two Poles of the black hole the
there's the emission of jets
relativistic Jets
extremely highly luminous Jets of
relativistic particles so let's go to
Google
and look at an let's say an artist's
representation of an active Galactic
nucleus active Galactic
nuclei um
yeah so that that's what it looks like
typically and we actually have images of
of jets here's one here's here's a good
image of an actual jet that's being
thrown out of an active Galactic nucleus
so this is what it looks like all right
and uh the polar regions of of the black
hole emit these relativistic Jets
extremely high energy High Velocity Jets
of charged
particles and that's what it is uh an
active Galactic Galactic nuclear if
they're extremely uh luminous they are
called
quazars uh and uh there are other
categories of these things as well if if
the Jets are coming directly towards the
Earth these these objects are called
blazars because they they Blaze forth
and so so yeah that's what it is so
that's the difference between a standard
super massive black hole that is living
its life and minding it own business
quietly not bothering anybody and an
active Galactic nucleus that's like
telling everybody hey here I am and you
better you know say so that's what it
is okay oh om Gaby 2778 says fun
question we may soon be in the Age of
Exploration space exploration and we may
see humans on Mars in 2050 okay what are
your thoughts on life once existing on
Mars and HP tically let's say there was
Life on Mars but similar to the
dinosaurs they not they are now fossils
but we haven't discovered it yet if we
find fossils on Mars how much of a
dramatic change will that be to the age
of age-old question of RV alone and also
your thoughts on the idea of God being
man manmade will it further entice us to
keep exploring okay let's talk about
Live From Mars there are lots of
questions in here we cannot unpack all
of these so yeah eventually hopefully if
things go well we will have humans on
Mars by the 2040s perhaps 2030s maybe
2040s and definitely hopefully 2050s
okay so we will have humans there what
are my thoughts on life possibly
existing on Mars in the past it's
possible Mars was a very earthlike
Planet a couple of billion years ago we
know that there was a tremendous amount
of flowing water on the surface of Mars
Mars had a much thicker
atmosphere in the past and
U and it's possible there was life on
the planet so if it was warm enough to
have liquid water flowing water oceans
and lakes and rivers of water and this
went on for a very long time then yes
it's possible that life may have emerged
on Mars U maybe independently of Life
emerging on Earth and there are some
some speculative questions right we we
have discovered certain Mars origin
meteorites on Earth and uh when the
cross-sections were taken and examined
through microscopes certain artifacts
are visible like which look look like
fossilized
bacteria uh what's the name of that Mars
asteroid a LH something or the other
shall we put that on the screen I mean
let's quickly take a look at that uh
once again our friend Google Mars
meteorite e LH yeah 84001 that's the one
come on so let's take a look at the
electron microscope image you can see
what looks like a tubular object that
could be a Proto
microorganism or something like that so
this isn't a conclusive evidence of of
Life having existed on Mars in the past
but it's a it's tell it's a Telltale
sign as you can see there are lots of
these these structures that look like
microorganisms fossilized microorganisms
here's another image of that and so on
so it's possible so it is definitely
possible that life may have existed on
Mars in the past maybe like you say
dinosaurs I'm not sure but dinosaurs
it's it's quite possible that uh
microbial life may have existed on Mars
and maybe maybe more advanced life forms
as well but we don't have any evidence
of
that so once we have humans there they
could do some digging or whatever and
you know maybe they will discover
something it's possible I'm open to the
possibility I'll be happy if if we
discover that and obviously if we
discover that there will be a
fundamental revision of the way we look
at the universe it'll prove that yes if
we discover that on Mars that it will it
will prove that life isn't unique to
Earth it existed on on on Mars in the
past maybe it still exist underground
possible
possible uh yeah so we we will get
answers to these questions eventually
once we reach there so yeah it's it's
interesting it's exciting that's why
space exploration is really exciting
because it it it gives us answers to so
many questions and it it broadens our
Horizons and we understand the world the
universe much better at least our our
neighboring Planet first of all we can
start with that
right samrat chakra says since Mass
lacks a magnetosphere will it ever be
possible to terraform it into a planet
like Earth and can we create an
artificial magnetosphere by running huge
electric strips around across the
circumference of the planet okay what is
a planet's magnetosphere Earth our
planet our home planet has magnet
magnetosphere it's this magnetic field
that is generated by through the Dynamo
effect in the internal through the
internal structure of the earth which is
molten iron and nickel and if you want
to see a cross-section of the earth
let's once again go back to the
images
uh Earth cross
section and if we look in this we
have let's take a look at at this
image so we have the crust that we are
familiar with then we have the upper
crust the low lower crust
um there's the
mantle and then there is the lower
mantle there's the inner core there's
the outer core and all that so there is
a gigantic magma layer and then there is
uh the inner core which is molten sorry
the external core which is molten metal
liquid iron and nickel and then there's
a solid internal uh internal inner core
so it is uh so this molten metal swirls
around and there are currents and Eddies
within it and it is likely that is it is
highly charged there are charged
particles that are ions in there and
that is what creates the Dy the causes
the Dynamo effect and creates the
magnetic field of the earth so the Earth
is a large planet compared to Mars the
Earth's radius is much greater than the
of
masss so we know what is the what is the
formula for the volume of a sphere
planets are not entirely spherical but
we can approximate them as being spheres
the formula for the volume of the SPH of
a sphere is 4X 3 pi R cubed where R is
cubed and the formula for the surface
area of a sphere if is 4 pi r s where R
is squared so the larger R is
the larger the smaller is the surface to
volume ratio and the smaller R is the
larger is the surface to volume ratio do
the calculations okay so when you have a
small planet the surface to volume ratio
is larger which means that the planet
the internal part of the planet the
inner whatever molten hot part of the
planet will cool
faster all the planets that we know of
have heat with in them inside that is a
left that is left over from the birth of
of the solar system and everything was
just
hot so Mars cooled faster than the than
Earth and that's why the the the liquid
metal part of Mars must be more or less
almost solid by now which means that
which is why it has a very weak magnetic
field and because it has a very weak or
non-existent magnetic field what that
did is that charged particle solar we
started impacting the atmosphere of Mars
directly and eventually they ionized the
atmosphere and stripped most of it away
and they Al that's why Mars is a very
thin vispy tenuous atmosphere compared
to the earth because this process
happened over more than a billion years
of time and that's also the reason why
it it Stripped Away the water from the
planet from the surface of the planet so
all the water that exists on Mars is
underground or at the polar
regions so yeah that's what happened in
Mars Mars now Mars lacks it an
magnetosphere is will it be possible to
terraform Mars it is possible to
terraform Mars over a period of let's
say a thousand years okay to be
realistic so we tear off our Mars we
give it a thick atmosphere and we we
increase the temperature of the planet
of the atmosphere to reasonably
earthlike levels and we ensure there is
flowing water again on the surface of
Mars and there are lakes and rivers and
oceans and all that we can do that
through a variety of means I'm not going
to the means one of the silliest things
is nuke Mars well that's also a dirty
way of doing it but not a good not
advisable so let's say we ter off from
Ms then what happens the planet doesn't
have a magnetosphere so is it worth
doing it
look the process of the stripping away
of the atmosphere because of the lack of
the magnetosphere this process took
about a billion years a billion with a
B we going to terraform mass in thousand
years and for us thousand a thousand
years is a tremendous amount of
time for us a 100 years is a long time
isn't it and if you look at known human
history it's about 10,000 years old and
nothing's going to happen in 10,000
years so uh it's definitely worthwhile
terraforming the planet and this if we
make it more earthlike in a thousand
years that that will last for at least a
few hundred thousand years so it makes a
lot of sense to do that and creating an
artificial magnet magnetosphere by using
running huge electric strips it's
extremely unfeasible because you will
need gigantic electric currents and
gigantic electric charges there are
tremendous amount of metal to do that
and it's not practical to do that so
creating an artificial magnetosphere in
this manner is Impractical but it is
definitely worthwhile terraforming the
planet and having the planet being
earthlike for a few hundred thousand
years that would be great
okay Amit Amit josi says recently human
experiments have begun at neural link
how where do you see this going could
this be a threat to humans could it
affect freedom of thoughts thank you uh
yes neuralink has is in the process of
of conducting human trials at least one
test subject has
been uh
announced and that person is is a
quadriplegic which means that that
person has lost the ability to to
control his or her limbs because of
paralysis or whatever and neuralink has
made made apparently a big difference in
that person's life uh so what is neural
link it's essentially a chip that's
inserted in the brain it's it's
implanted into the brain matter and uh
it can perform a variety of functions
like uh injecting data directly into
your brain interfacing the brain
directly with computers external
computers so so you can just sit like
this cross your arms and control your
mouse cursor or or or or your smartphone
or your tablet just through your
thoughts and you'll be able to play
YouTube videos in your mind eventually
you you'll be able to watch movies with
your eyes closed in your mind download
music up I don't know anything's
possible so is is this a Potential
Threat for humans yes in the future it
could be a threat you could use it for a
variety of things you could if everybody
has a neural link or or some kind of
chip implanted you could tripple human
brains by injecting garbage data into
them or or you know impacting certain
functions of the brain maybe even
causing a stroke maybe even shutting
down somebody's heart anything's
possible down the line right I'm not
saying neuralink is is doing any of that
neuralink I'm sure has well at least the
stated objective is to make a difference
a difference for the good for Humanity
but this technology any technology has
multiple uses every technology is is
double edged sword nuclear technology
can be used for good as well as for bad
a stick can be used for good as well as
for bad and so on so this technology
could end up opening a Pandora's Box as
any new technology can like AI can for
example so yes it could affect it could
even affect the freedom of thought who
knows y chaturv says have you seen the
new versions of open AIS and Google's
new AI models should we be worried and
what do you think this will do in the
future I haven't seen all the latest
versions there are so many AIS out there
there is Cloe there is uh
B There is Gro Grog Greg I don't know
what it's called there is chat GPT and I
don't know how many other models are out
there I haven't seen all of them I've
seen maybe one or two uh should should
we be worried well it's definitely
something that could be used to to a
great to do a great amount of good to do
a great amount of harm to control
Humanity to monitor Humanity to
supervise Humanity a lot a lot so it's a
it's it's kind of scary it's possibly
very danger and uh it could even if uh
the AI system doesn't become self-aware
and conscious and even if it doesn't
become an artificial general
intelligence it will give a tremendous
amount of power in the hands of those
who wield these systems the ones who
control and own these systems so it
doesn't the AI system doesn't need to be
self-aware and super intelligent and
uh uh all
that it doesn't need to be an AGI it
will it already has enough power to
completely change the future course of
humanity I mean right now the the lowest
level impact we're thinking of is that
jobs will become obsolete professions
will become obsolute data entry
professions the data entry profession
will become obsolete fact checking will
become obsolete um proof reading will
become obsolete uh research assistance
will go out of business digital artists
musicians will go out of business so
many thing so many skill sets are
becoming redundant that's the lowest
level impact but there are many more
high level impacts of artificial
intelligence like you know it could
control people's uh thoughts and beliefs
and narratives that that the believe in
every person could eventually be given a
tailored version of the news that they
not even aware of that everybody else is
getting their own specific tailored
version of news so news will come in
flavors books will come in flavors
everybody will have books written
specifically for them on demand music
will come in according to your tastes
and it will essentially create all these
Divergent human beings who
are who are not even aware of what's
happening in the world that's why
version of what could happen and much
more it could give rise to super
intelligent
robots armies of robots then so all
Warfare could
be could be all future warfare could be
AIS and and robots fighting each other
and possibly attacking humans also
that's the Terminator scenario isn't it
and so on so yeah there are so many
dangerous possibilities in scary
possibilities in the future that is
indeed true
AAL Chan says what are your thoughts on
umam mua is it was this a comet or an
extraterrestrial piece of
technology similarly how can Black
Knight be space drunk when no country
has capabilities to launch satellites at
the time are these just hoaxes or there
some truth to them I have no idea what
what Black Knight is I've heard some
rumors I've not looked into it so I
cannot answer the question about Black
Knight umu mua okay so umu mua is this
object
space object Space Rock looks like or
space thing okay that was discovered a
few years ago and it was traveling at at
a very high speed very high velocity and
its trajectory was hyperbolic it wasn't
parabolic a parabola is a closed loop a
hyperbola is an open loop so it came it
went around the sun and it went off at
very high velocity in a hyperbolic
trajectory which means it's it's on a
trajectory that will lead it out of the
solar system it's going to go up it's
going to escape it's on an escape path
at an with an escape velocity okay which
means that it came from outside it
wasn't born in the solar system so it's
an object it's an Interstellar object
which came from outside and it's on the
way back outside and it's right now I
don't know where it is but it's still
within the solar system it's going to be
within the solar system for a few
decades
more and it had certain interesting
characteristics uh it was highly
reflective almost like a Solar Shield or
something almost was like it was made of
polished metal that's that's of
reflectivity apparently okay and it is
said that it it changed velocity over
time so it it did not travel with a
standard you know parabol hyperbolic
trajectory with with the standard
velocity you know you can calculate the
velocity of an object like that but it
actually changed its velocity It sped up
over time at a certain phase of its
trajectory so that is kind
of well that that kind of tell would
indicate if if it is true that it had
some propulsion on it it was able to
change its
velocity so I believe it is the uh
astrophysicist AI lub who said that this
was most likely alien
technology but do we have evidence of it
apart from whatever we have measured
briefly and rudimentarily we don't have
much more evidence so there is a
proposal that we could send a spacecraft
to catch up with this object umam MUA in
the next 20 or so years when it will be
maybe somewhere around the vicinity of
the gas giants those orbits so by 2050
or so we if we launch a spacecraft by
let's say
2030 we can have it catch up with umu
amua by by about 2050 in 20 in 20 years
or so in two decades if we do that then
we'll be we'll be able to get a better
idea proper idea of what this objector
really is but beyond that as of today we
cannot see say much Beyond speculating
based on whatever data is
available samrat says why do volcanoes
why do volcanoes for why do volcanoes
occur on Islands do volcanoes
form in mainlands too yes it's not just
Islands I mean yeah there are lots of
volcanoes on Islands Japan is number of
is a bunch of islands it's an island
nation and there are lots of volcanos on
on Japanese
territory if you look at sakhalin if you
look at the Kamchatka Peninsula and so
on there are lots of volcanoes there
there's lots of volcanoes in Indonesia
which is Islands then there are a couple
of volcano in the Andaman Islands region
the narak condam and the baron Island
volcanoes one of these is active or
somewhat active not dormant then you
have the Greek Islands the there is
Santorini which is a volcano then you
have egyp you you have Italy which is
kind of part of this region it has ethna
Mount ethna Mount
vus um and so on and there's a bunch of
volcanoes in South America aaga
poel and so on I think Akon kaga is a
volcano I think is Akon kaga a volcano
let's let's just uh double check that is
Akon kagwa
aona is it
volcano is it a
volcano okay is Akon kaga a
volcano I think it
is okay it used to be an active Str
volcano long ago and it's now probably a
dormant volcano okay so a is one uh po
that's another stratto volcano It's
seems to be active and so on so you have
these volcano like akaga popat petel
which are not on Islands these are very
much on what you call the
mainland and there's many more where is
Akon kaga poocat is in
Mexico
Aon sorry
aona all right we'll have to zoom out to
discover where it
is okay it's in Chile aona and and
there's more there's more of these
things okay there's more of these
volcanoes and then you have volcanoes in
the US as well what was it called us USA
volcano let's just type USA
volcano so Yellowstone is this giant uh
uh super
volcano uh and this
Mount what is it Rainer was it Mount
Rainer volcano
let's
n and so on so I I'll not waste your
time by looking at different volcanoes
over here the point is that you have
volcanoes on Islands you also have
volcano on Mainland now why are volcano
what what is the cause of volcanos
volcanos typically
uh occur in in in parts of the Earth
where there is a defect in the crust of
the earth and the magma is able to come
out so that is typically when you have
the
the junction of different tectonic
plates so you have tectonic
plates the subduction of one tectonic
plate going under the other and these
are also Volcan these are also
earthquake zones so there's something
called The Ring of Fire the Japan
Indonesia and Andaman region where you
have so many volcanoes and so many
earthquakes and so on so
volcanoes are because of defects in the
Earth crust where you have tectonic
activity tectonic plates either going
rubbing against each other or going
below one going going below the other
that's where you have
these that's where the magma has the
opportunity to come out and that's what
causes volcanism and that can also
happen on mainlands but more on islands
and more at the intersection of these
tectonic
plates
okay ad Guru Prasad says what does the
word dust cloud mean which was the thing
that formed our solar system it cannot
be the dust that uh we see on Earth okay
so our solar system was formed out of
what we call a solar nebula so initially
it was a solar nebula and it it formed a
protostellar dis and it that eventually
gave rise to the Sun and all the planets
so what was the composition of this
solar nebula this solar nebula was
primarily composed of just gas and what
gas primarily hydrogen and helium which
are the two most abundant elements of
the universe and there were Trace
Amounts of other elements like silicon
and oxygen and carbon iron and whatnot
other heavier elements okay but the gas
was just hydrogen and helium and the
dust was these tiny solar particles made
of these elements like Silicon um Iron
oxygen carbon and other heavier elements
like I just said so there was gas and
there was dust and the all of this
together made up the solar nebula so
these particles this gas and this dust
it originated from previous generations
of stars that had already gone through
their life cycles and
died and ejected all this material into
space so that was the origin of this
Stellar or solar nebula made of gas and
made of dust so it's not the dust that
we find on the earth it is these tiny
solid particles made of these elements
that were born in the furnace in the
hearts of older
stars the sun is a reincarnated star and
it it it formed out of this
large nebula this large molecular cloud
and this molecular cloud this nebula
most likely experience some kind of
disturbance like a shock wave from a
neighboring Supernova or something which
caused it to collapse under its own
gravity and that's how the Sun and these
other planets Etc were born and these
dust particles that you are referring to
were the building blocks of the
terrestrial planets Mercury Venus Earth
and Mars and they were also the building
blocks of the course of the of the gas
giants which are the gas giants Jupiter
Saturn Uranus and Neptune so yeah that
that's what it is so that's the gas
that's the dust cloud that you're
mentioning it was not just the dust
cloud it was a cloud made of hydrogen
helium and all these uh particles of
these various
elements om g a b c Etc are the chances
of intelligent life existing on a planet
similar to Earth just a chance of
probability let's assume life exists on
an earth like Planet but are the chances
of an intelligent species such as humans
just a probabilistic chance because of
our closed relatives like the dandal
died out we have gotten very lucky
surviving for thousands of years like I
I mentioned like I mentioned earlier uh
there are these great filters that
everybody every every species every
intelligent species has to go through
for us to exist today lots of things had
to go right life had to somehow emerge
on the planet and we don't know how it
emerged then it had to go from
unicellular cellular to multicellular
life forms then they had these life
forms had to survive multiple Extinction
events they had to emerge out of the
oceans and onto the dry dry land and and
then there to evolve in a variety of
ways there to survive the chi chulu
impact event 66 million years ago that
killed off the non-avian dinosaurs then
the life form had to become bipedal and
become more intelligent and then survive
lots of extinctions like the extinction
of Homo habilis homo erus homo
Neanderthal and then Homo sapiens
survives and who knows what other
problems we will see in the future
nuclear war is a dangerous possibility
climate change more Extinction events
more meteors or or comat asteroids
coming in and so on so the chances are
very slim but since you have so many
stars and planets out there in the
observable universe more than 10 rais to
21 it it would make sense that there is
intelligent intelligent life out there
and then the question arises where is it
and we don't know so maybe it's a
probabilistic chance that it just
somehow emerg we don't know how life
emerged we know that every every life
form on this planet whether it is
multicellular beings like us whe whether
it is microorganisms like water bear
whether it is bacteria unicellular
organisms whether whether it's even
viruses all of these organisms have DNA
now DNA is an extraordinarily complex
molecule it just doesn't just
spontaneously emerge the question is how
did where did it come from how did
something like this evolve an extremely
even the simplest microorganisms have
such incredibly complicated
DNA simpler than ours but still more
very complicated how does a molecule
like that evolve and how does it develop
the ability to replicate and jump inside
these these
bags these membranes called cells and
develop all the
organel the golgy bodies the
mitochondria the endoplasmic reticulum
and whatnot Celia how does all this
happen how does this happen in Just 4
billion years 4.5 years and when first
life that emerged was unicellular it
happened it emerged about 3.7 billion
years before
today uh Which is less than a billion
years after the Earth was born how did
such complex life emerge in just less
than a billion years so we don't have
answers to these questions so maybe it's
chance maybe there was
seeding somehow on our planet from with
some mechanism we don't know there lots
of questions we can't answer right
now pram Sharma says maybe a rookie
question not not an issue you can ask
rookie questions so we see photographs
of various nebulas Stars also the first
ever black hole image how do we capture
them which Spectra waves do we capture
how does it work okay when we see images
of galaxies we typically use visible
light telescopes so these
telescopes gives us give us images
invisible light the kind of light our
eyes can see in that in the visible part
of the electromagnetic spectrum then so
most of the Stars galaxies nebulas
planets whatever we we see whatever
images we see are generally taken with
earth-based telescopes or the Hubble
Space Telescope which all see things in
the visible spectrum then you have the
Chandra xray Observatory which takes
images in the X-ray Spectrum that's
something we can't see but yeah it it
gives you a different view of the world
uh and then you have something the gwst
the James web Space Telescope that looks
at the universe in the
infrared part of the spectrum it shows
us it it detects the oldest light okay
the the the light that's the most
stretched out because of the expansion
of the universe and so on so we use
these different parts of the spectrum we
use different instruments that can
access different Paths of the spectrum
to to form this this
image of various parts of the universe
various components of the universe and
that's how we discover more things about
how the universe
evolved and how it was how we came to be
the way we are right now what about the
black hole image so the image okay let's
let's uh go to Google once
again
m87
image okay this
one so this is the image of the m87
super massive black hole let's put this
on the
screen um this is the original one very
diffus and this seems to be a improved
one if I'm not mistaken in polarized
light and you can see the the the fine
structure so to say yeah so how was this
image taken does it actually show the
black hole it does not show the black
hole it shows the accretion disc and the
Magnetic lines and the and the yeah the
magnetic lines of force almost you could
say
so this is not an image of a black hole
this is the image of the accretion disc
around the black hole the gluing
accretion disc and you can see there's
this Central darkness which is the
actual black hole and there are
relativistic effects over here which
means that there's a lot of
uh curvature bending of light and all
that and it it once again uh turns out
that it is exactly in line with what
general relativity says so so the black
hole image was also
taken in which I don't remember which
wavelength it was taken on taken in
visible light was it or was it
millimeter
length waves I don't remember right now
doesn't matter but yeah so to look at
the image to look at the universe you
can use different parts of the
electromagnetic spectrum to get
different kinds of information and
that's how it
works okay use DJ something or the other
says can quantum mechanics explain
Consciousness quantum mechanics and
Consciousness look
uh we don't know if quantum mechanics
can explain Consciousness first of all
we don't have a clear definition of
Consciousness you ask a biologist you
ask a neuroscientist you ask a
neurologist you ask an information
theorist you ask a physicist they will
all give you
different ATT they will all attempt to
define consciousness in different ways
then nobody will be able to actually
properly define consciousness so we
don't have a definition of Consciousness
first of all which means that the
Consciousness is currently not a subject
of scientific inquiry it's a subject of
philosophical inquiry because there's no
scientific definition first of all we
don't know what Consciousness is if I
have a system a black box how do I know
there's a Consciousness
inside what are the characteristics
that it would exhibit that would tell me
it's conscious it's kind of asking the
question what is life what's the
definition of life we don't even have a
clear definition of life when we see
life we know it's life but can we Define
it there are C there is a certain set of
definitions but still not it's kind of
vague I mean take a virus a virus is
kind of on the dividing line between
between alive and not
alive it exhibits some qualities some
properties of
crystals it also has DNA it also has
self-replication or assisted
replication but it
doesn't uh it doesn't
uh exist in homeostasis with its EnV
environment it doesn't affect or or
modify the environment it just exists so
so it's it's difficult to even Define
life similarly it's Define it's
difficult to it's right now it's
impossible to define consciousness
then when there's a phenomenon that you
don't have a definition for then how can
quantum mechanics which is
science explain that and then of course
there are attempts to do that there is
the orc o theory of hammer Hoff and
Penrose that says that the microt
tubules that are inside your
brain they you can you can sustain
Quantum superpositions Etc in these
microtubules and that could be the basis
of consciousness
that's one Theory do we have evidence
and proof of that not sure we
do so there are attempts that are being
made to see if Consciousness can be
explained via quantum mechanics the
hammer of Penrose theory is definitely
in line with that it says that these
microt tubules they can
sustain Quantum superpositions within
them once again brain the brain is is a
wet warm environment and decoherence
would happen very readily in there so
there's a question about whether it's
possible and then there's a question of
what is is is consciousness an emergent
phenomenon does it emerge out of
complexity does it emerge out of low
entropy States in highly complex systems
and so on we don't have any of the
answers right now so we can't say for
sure whether quantum mechanics can
explain Consciousness or not or not
okay curious Prat says what's the
bootstrap Paradox please explain have
you heard of the grandfather Paradox
okay there's this
hypothetical evil guy very evil guy okay
very very bad guy he makes a time
machine he goes back in time 80 years he
locates his grandfather and kills his
grandfather okay then so the grandfather
is and he kills the grandfather when the
grandfather was still a kid
so the guy goes back in time kills his
own grandfather before he was before his
grandfather was able to produce any
children then how does he
exist so how does the killer exist if he
is able to go back in time and kill the
grandfather who is his the source of his
origin
anyway so that is the grandfather
Paradox and the bootstrap Paradox is
kind of uh you know it's it's in in line
with that the bootstrap Paradox is is
this this causal Paradox causality so
what you have is that you have an object
that
exists and it should not exist it what
caused it so let's say you make a you
build a time machine okay let's say it's
possible to build a time machine you go
back in time and let's say I have this
object okay see this is an object that I
have and I go back in time to the time
when I was 5 years old and I give this
object to
myself and that's how I acquire the
object so
that would tell you that this object has
no origin nobody made this
object so that kind of breaks down
causality causality breaks down so that
is one of the problems with the
with uh time travel so the bootstrap
Paradox is essentially called a causal
Loop Paradox but what what I'm talking
about is a causal
Loop let's
say uh
I want to write a book or let's say I've
written a book and
I I go back in time and give it to my
younger self who studies this book and
writes the book so then what's the
origin of the book that sort of thing
okay so it's it's what you see is there
is a violation of causality I mean the
universe is supposed to be causal every
effect must have a cause but in this
scenario that we that we're discussing
the cause and effect Loop happens in
such a way that makes it unclear where
the original cause
originated and then this brings us to
philosophical questions about the nature
of existence the nature of creation if
an object can exist without an origin if
information cannot exist With An Origin
it challenges the idea that everything
must come from somewhere it
also raises question about time about
temporal logic consistency of timelines
can something exist if it was never
created in the first place and so on and
so forth so this is the boot bootstrap
Paradox it is a causal Loop Paradox it's
a temporal
Paradox Arijit benerji says is time
travel possible using worm holes worm
holes so a wormhole is a is an Einstein
Rosen Bridge Okay uh it's one of the
solutions it's it's a class of solutions
of the Einstein field equations so if
wormholes a worm Wormhole is like a
shortcut between two locations in space
time not just in space but in space time
itself okay and if worm holes do exist
they could potentially allow po time
travel and how would this happen so a
world okay let's go to Google and and
try to visualize a wormhole one second
let's put this on the screen wormhole
so a wormhole is this sort of
uh it's it's a shortcut as you can see
here between two
locations in
SpaceTime uh and if one of these if one
you can see this Wormhole over here on
the screen if one end of the
Wormhole could be moved at a very high
speed relative to the other other end of
the Wormhole or alternatively if one end
of the if one end of the world were mold
could be placed in a strong
gravitational field then you would
experience time
dilation at that end of the worm hold
which is predicted by special as well as
general relativity okay so you'll have
time dilation where time moves slower
for an object or a person who is at that
end of the
Wormhole so in that mouth of the
Wormhole you will experience time
dilation which which would mean that the
two wormholes are at different points in
time and this setup creates what's
called closed Tim like curves these are
paths in SpaceTime that look that loop
back upon themselves and this
theoretically would allow you to travel
back to the past so an object that
emerges that that enters the Wormhole at
one end could potentially emerged at a
time before it entered okay so yeah so
that that's the deal now the question is
can worm holes actually exist are
wormholes traversable I mean for a
wormhole to be traversable it would need
some exotic matter within it otherwise
wormholes want to snapshot that's what
the the throats of wormholes want to
snapshot that's what the equations tell
us so you would need some exotic matter
in the Wormhole to keep the throat open
something like matter with negative
energy density or negative Mass which is
exotic matter which we've never seen
ever but yeah you would need that or you
would need uh you would need a cosmic
string in there that simply can't break
and that could keep the vermal open for
it to be traversible but could you still
survive that and and so on so forth so
yeah theoretically possible but is it
practically possible we don't know but
theoretically one can actually conceive
of thought experiment thought
experiments and scenarios in which one
could actually do
this herel Sharma says is intelligence
merely a product of chemical reactions
or is it present at the beginning of
everything int intelligence okay you
know there are lots
of there are many scientists who like to
claim that you know intelligence is just
a product of chemical reactions emotions
are the product of chemical
reactions the question I would like to
ask is what's the empirical evidence for
this what's the empirical evidence that
a specific emotion is the consequence of
the specific set of chemical reactions
that happen in a specific location in
the brain at a specific point in time
how do we know this we don't know
this when you make a claim you need to
have evidence that backs up your claim
so these claims are just made flippantly
and generally without any empirical
observable reproducible evidence to back
up this claim
so I'll tell you just because somebody
is a scientist doesn't mean that person
is intelligent okay I'll I'll tell you
that there are lots of scientists who
aren't the most intelligent
people so I don't agree that
intelligence is necessarily a mere
product of chemical reactions or
emotions are merely it's possible it is
possible but we don't have evidence for
it when we talking about something like
intelligence we talk when we're talking
about emotions we're talking about
Consciousness and we don't know what
Consciousness is we don't know the
mechanis M through which Consciousness
emerges where it how it exists where
does it come from we don't know that
yeah it looks like it's it's
Consciousness is it it is located up
here in the brain the brain region
that's how we that's where we see the
world from but we don't really
understand how the brain works at all
and we don't we know next to nothing
about Consciousness so I say we don't
know I would that's my answer is we
don't
know okay so we are almost at the end of
today's thing I have many more questions
but I have already crossed two hours so
I won't be able to take
those um should I take one more question
okay one more question Amit josi says
the particles if the particles from the
standard model like quarks electrons
neutros Etc are Elementary then why do
they split up in other particles in
nuclear reactions like beta DK where an
up Quark splits into a down quark
positron and neutrino and the other way
around for down Quark with electron and
anti neutrino look first of all what are
Elementary particles the particles in
the standard model like quarks electrons
neutros and so on so forth are are
considered to be Elementary particles in
the sense that they are not made up of
smaller particles smaller constituent
particles these are the basic building
blocks of matter of matter and of the
fundamental interactions now the process
that you're describing in nuclear
reactions like beta DK Etc it does not
involve these particles splitting into
to others it involves these particles
transforming through fundamental
interactions so beta dek beta dek is is
a type of nuclear reaction where a
neutron transforms into a proton that's
beta minus DK or a proton transforms
into a neutron which is a beta plus DK
these are transformations of particles
these are not splitting of particles and
behind this at the bottom of this is the
weak nuclear force so the weak nuclear
force is behind the beta beta plus Decay
beta minus decay in beta minus Decay a
neutron which is composed of an up quark
and two down quarks it transforms into a
proton which is two up quarks and one
down quark and this happens this
transformation happens because of the
weak interaction and one of the down
quarks transforms into an up Quark
through the weak nuclear force there's
the emission of a w minus
boson and which will Decay into an
electron and an electron neutrino and so
on and so forth so this is how it
happens so it is not an elementary
particle splitting into another one it's
is transformations of Elementary
particles and emissions of bosons and
electrons and
neutros through the process of the weak
nuclear force and there is a weak force
and there are Quark flavors and there is
so much more in this there's emission of
W bosons W plus W minus and so on so my
point is there is no splitting quarks do
not not split into other particles they
transform into different kinds of quarks
through the weak interaction and this is
accompanied by the emission of w bosons
that then Decay into
leptons electrons or positrons and
neutros so that is what happens and that
is the process no splitting
Transformations and Transformations
mediated by the weak Force as described
by the standard model of particle
physics all right okay uh that should be
the last question let me take a couple
of questions from the live chat in case
you any have any
questions let's let's take a couple of
questions from the live chat
geopolitical du says why is desalination
of ocean water so expensive and how does
it work desalination of ocean water see
the ocean water is mostly water Plus
Salt various kinds of salt the major
salt is sodium chloride which is your
common table salt so what you want to do
is you want to desalinate this water
so how do you do it you well one of the
simplest ways is to boil it so that it
evaporates then this evaporated steam
water vapor you trap it you cool it down
and condense it into pure water without
any salt and What's Left Behind is the
brain which eventually becomes just dry
salt and whatever else particulate
matter so it takes a tremendous amount
of energy heat energy let's say to to
desalinate just one liter
of water ocean water you boil it you
condense it the condensate is pure water
and What's Left Behind is the what you
don't want the salt and whatever else so
you need to burn something you need a
heat Source fuel that fuel could be coal
it could
be petroleum gas it could be solar or
whatever but the point is it takes a lot
of energy to do that and that's why it
is
expensive that's how it works and that's
why desalination is expensive
Ric Raj Multiverse existence Multiverse
there are two major ways of arriving at
a Multiverse one is the string theory
Multiverse like I explained some time
ago then raised to 500 possible
different kinds of universes each with
different physical laws we don't know
which one is ours so that's that's
that's the string theory landscape or
the string theory Multiverse and the
other
Multiverse is what emerges out
of the many worlds interpretation of
quantm
mechanics and that's all about the
spreading up of timelines based on
various factors I'll not go into the
details I have videos on this channel
which I've explained it in in much more
detail so two different categories of
Multiverse the string theory Multiverse
the string theory landscape and the
Multiverse that emerges out of the many
worlds interpretation of quantum
mechanics all right let's take one more
question one more
question uh JP peda says can technology
and Robotics solve the total fertility
rate issue yeah the global total
fertility rates are plummeting dropping
everywhere including in India I ask
because many women don't want to have
children and are more interested in
Career Education all right Pursuits
rather than having children okay so how
can technology and Robotics solve the
TFR problem I'm just trying to figure it
out do we create artificial incubators
in which uh you incubate embryos who are
carried to full term like in that movie
The
Matrix like that I mean it could be
possible but there I'm sure there are
lots of uh technological challenges in
in making this possible I mean this
artificial womb environment needs to be
very humanlike I mean it should be able
to sustain the the growing embryo fetus
and provide it with all the nutrition
and everything it needs and obviously
it's not as simple as just that it's not
a machine it's a human being and the
human being needs to be in the in the
body of its mother and experience the
sensations that fetus has experiened
while they are within the within the
womb and uh if that is not there then
will it develop properly so there are
lots of questions that we don't have
answers to right now and this sort of
experimentation is obviously clearly
unethical I mean some people would do it
with primates and monkeys in my opinion
even that would be cruel and unethical
so I don't know I don't know know can
you just set up baby factories in this
manner uh right now I don't think it's
even technologically feasible to do it
in the future in some dystopian future
somebody may try this but well I think
the the best way to solve the TFR is to
do it the good oldfashioned way I would
say okay I think I'm going to end over
here Karan says will will you make any
Physics course in the future if there is
demand for I make it I mean that's this
is the field I enjoy the most om beer
says if time slows down inside the black
hole will the object that fell into the
black hole survive till the black hole
disappears due to relays of radiation we
don't know look an object if it falls
inside a black hole depending on the
size of black hole will be stretched it
will be it will undergo a process called
spaghettification so if a human being
goes into a black hole and the black
hole is small enough the human being
will be stretched into stretched into
ribbons if it's a gigantic black hole
there will be no spaghetti so it's
paradoxically weird that the smaller
black hole is the more spaghettification
ex happens when when an object goes
inside
so uh the object depending on the size
of the black hole wants want survive and
we don't know what happens inside once
you cross the Event Horizon what happens
inside we don't know I mean according to
general relativity there is a
singularity at the center which would
which means infinite curvature infinite
mass and energy density which would be
the destruction of any object that falls
inside all the way there so from the
various
views of a black hole that we have it
looks like objects don't survive once
they go inside okay that is the last
question for today I will see you in the
next uh live stream which is tomorrow
tomorrow is going to be a totally
different set of topics geopolitics
history and current affairs but thank
you so much for participating in this
thank you for so much for asking all
your questions I really appreciate it
and I will see you in next week's
science astrophysics Etc live stream
I'll do it every week I really enjoy it
so thank you for so much and I'll see
you in the next one whichever one
you uh attend thank you bye-bye